Guide to the Thomas Percy Correspondence
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Thomas Percy correspondence
1770-1807
OSB MSS 39
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
0.21
(1 box)
Correspondence, mainly concerning Percy's duties as a Court preacher, including the scheduling of sermons with various other clergymen. Almost every letter is accompanied by a typed transcription. There is also correspondence from Henry Meen about literature; Meen's work on translations from Greek; and his correction of proofs for Percy.
Percy, Thomas, 1729-1811
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Cleanth Brooks in 1979.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
THOMAS PERCY, 1729-1811
Thomas Percy, the son of a grocer, was born in Bridgnorth, Shropshire on April 13, 1729. Educated at Christ Church, Oxford, Percy was ordained in the Church of England in 1753 and held the livings of Easton Maudit and Wilby; served as chaplain to the Duke of Northumberland and chaplain-in-ordinary to King George III; and became Dean of Carlisle in 1778 and Bishop of Dromore (Ireland) in 1782.
Percy published a number of literary and antiquarian works, including the narrative poem The Hermit of Warkworth (1770); translations and adaptations from Chinese, Icelandic, Hebrew, and Spanish; and an edition of the "household book" of the Earl of Northumberland for 1513. He is best known, however, for Reliques of Ancient English Poetry, a three-volume collection of early English and Scottish ballad texts which included the first publication of "Sir Patrick Spens" and "Edward, Edward," among others. Reliques inspired two generations of antiquarians and poets both to preserve and study early ballads and to compose original poems in the form.
Percy married Anne Gutteridge in 1759. The couple had six children, of whom only two daughters survived. Thomas Percy died in Dromore on September 30, 1811, and is buried in Dromore Cathedral.
For further biographical information on Thomas Percy, see the Dictionary of National Biography, Volume XV; and the Dictionary of Literary Biography, Volume 104.
Scope and Contents
The Thomas Percy Correspondence consists almost entirely of letters to Thomas Percy. The papers span the dates 1770-1809 and have been organized into one series, Letters, which is arranged alphabetically by correspondent. Almost all of the letters are accompanied by typed transcripts.
The majority of the letters, including those by Nicholas Boscawen, Zachary Brook, John Cleaver, Thomas Francklin, and Andrew Wood, date from Percy's service as Chaplain-in-Ordinary to King George III and concern the scheduling of sermons before the court at St. James and of times for "waiting on the King."
The only letter by Percy in the collection is addressed to Thomas Wilkinson and congratulates him on enjoying an "independent Competency" without the "Splendid slavery" of a public position.
The letters of Henry Meen, classical scholar and rector of St. Nicholas Cole Abbey, are located in folders 9-17. Subjects include Meen's proposed edition of the works of Lycophron and his articles for the European Magazine; corrections to proofs for Percy, including one on blank verse before Milton which was destroyed in a fire at the publishers; and other literary and antiquarian topics.
Folder 25 contains a transcript of an announcement of Percy's translation of the Song of Solomon and an unidentified bibliographical note on a Latin ode.
English poetry -- 18th century; Preaching -- Great Britain; Sermons, English -- Great Britain -- 18th century; Clergy -- Great Britain; Meen, Henry, 1744-1817; Percy, Thomas, 1729-1811
- Letters, 1770-1809; Series I; 0.21' (1 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Letters, is arranged alphabetically by correspondent.
  - BOSCAWEN, NICHOLAS, 1720-1793
    - 2 AL in the third person and 1 ALS to Thomas Percy; London, 1772-76 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - BROOKE, ZACHARY, 1716-1788
    - ALS to Thomas Percy; Cambridge, n.y. Nov 20 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - CLEAVER, JOHN, CA. 1737-1776
    - 2 ALS to Thomas Percy; Oxford, 1770 Jul (Box 1, Folder 3)
      With: Percy's reply to letter of Jul 17; 1p (fragment), dated Jul 23
  - DALRYMPLE, JOHN, SIR, 1726-1810
    - 3 AL to Thomas Percy; [London] (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - DOW, ALEXANDER, D. 1779
    - ALS to Thomas Percy; London, 1772 Mar 14 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      With: "A Specimen of Oriental Elegy from the Persian of Diwan Shorit;" manuscript
  - FRANCKLIN, THOMAS, 1721-1784
    - 7 ALS to Thomas Percy, 1770-76 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - HATSELL, J.
    - ALS to Thomas Percy; Angel Inn, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - HUNTER, DAVID
    - ALS to Thomas Percy; St. Andrews, 1770 Apr 14 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - MALONE, EDMOND, 1741-1812
    - ALS to [John] Nichols; Foley Pl., 1809 Aug 9 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - MEEN, HENRY, D. 1817
    - 5 ALS to Thomas Percy, 1796 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - 6 ALS to Thomas Percy, 1797 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - ALS to Thomas Percy, 1799 Nov 25 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - ALS to Thomas Percy, 1800 Aug 29 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - ALS to Thomas Percy, 1801 Apr 8 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - 2 ALS to Thomas Percy, 1802 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - ALS to Thomas Percy, 1803 autumn (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - ALS to Thomas Percy, 1804 Jul 30 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - ALS to Thomas Percy, 1807 Jan 20 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      With: extract of review of Meen, 1815
  - NICHOLS, JOHN, 1745-1826
    - ALS to [Thomas Percy]; [London], [1802] Aug (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - NORMANTON, CHARLES AGAR, EARL OF, 1736-1809
    - ALS to Thomas Percy; Dublin, 1773 Oct 26 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - PERCY, THOMAS, 1729-1811
    - ALS to Thomas Wilkinson; Carlisle, 1783 May 27 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Accompanied by engraved portrait of Percy
  - SELBY, HENRY C.
    - ALS to Thomas Percy; Northumberland House, 1786 Jul 12 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - STEEVENS, GEORGE, 1736-1800
    - ALS to Edmond Malone; London, [1792] Jan (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Letter (copy) to Henry Meen; Hampstead Heath, 1793 (Box 1, Folder 23)
      In Meen's hand. With: draft of Meen's reply, and a memorandum by Meen
  - WOOD, ANDREW, CA. 1715-1772
    - ALS to Thomas Percy; Gateshead, 1770 Jul 22 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - UNIDENTIFIED
    - Unidentified note and transcript of advertisement (Box 1, Folder 25)